So, what happens if you go along and um
you know, you're just like in a normal
uh period of time, you miss a payment
and you have either hundreds of
thousands or millions of dollars in debt
that you're not able to pay back. It's
incredibly stressful. What happens if I
default on my 7-day loan? So, typically,
if someone misses a payment, that's
typically at the 60-day mark, the loan
can get flagged and transferred to
special assets. Does it make sense if
you're if you're in a cash crunch and
you're thinking, I think I might not be
able to make this payment. Does it make
sense to do something like call somebody
first before you? Communication is the
most important thing at the end of the
day. I think we ended up doing over a
100red million worth of express loans
last year.
Hi, I'm Sarah Sharp. I'm a deal attorney
who helps folks buy and sell businesses,
primarily accounting practices. And this
is the dealmakers podcast episode with
Eric Rabinovich of Liveo. he's a
dealmaker and that he's a banker and I'm
excited to hear some lessons and red
flags that he has seen in this industry.
Eric, um could you give a little
background about who you are and how you
came to be involved with deals.
Absolutely. Yeah, thank you Sarah.
Thanks for having me and uh hopefully
some folks get a little bit of value
from the conversation today. So I'm Eric
Rubinovich. I'm a loan officer on Live
Oak's professional services lending team
and that's one of about 40 industries
that Live Oak specializes in. So myself,
the team that I'm on, we focus
exclusively on lending to CPAs,
bookkeepers, accountants, tax preparers.
To a lesser degree, there's law firms
and architectural and engineering firms,
but 95% of the time we're working with
CPAs and bookkeepers and tax
professionals. And within that, most of
the deals we originate are are M&A.
They're uh folks buying other firms.
There's a a small percentage of folks
buying commercial real estate or
refinancing debt. Uh, as you probably
know, the SBA program is very flexible.
You can use it for all types of things,
but that's that's what I do. I'm based
in Washington DC. The bank is
headquartered in Wilmington, North
Carolina. We lend nationwide, so it
doesn't matter where the customer is.
And beyond that, uh, we are the number
one SBA lender. So, uh, we do a lot of
these types of loans. And that's, as
I'll talk about more, very relevant to
today's discussion. this. Thank you,
Eric. And I am glad to have you on. As
you know, um a question that I get as a
lawyer a lot and as a just not the
banker in the ecosystem of the deals
that I do is what happens if I default
on my 7-day loan? And then just kind of
subsidiary questions related to that. I
actually got an email this week with
some questions in it um about somebody
who has a loan and it's personally
guaranteed of course and they're
considering buying some real estate and
they're worried about you know how how
that house will you know fit into the
context of the collateral with the loan
and things like that. But what is um I
think kind of hindrance to people is
when you're going for an SBA loan, you
don't want to ask your loan, you know,
your your folks at the bank, hey, I I'm
really worried I'll default. Like what
happens if that happens? Um it's a
little bit of a red flag. Um so I think
uh folks want to present their most
confident face when they're which they
should. So perhaps it could be of value
to have more of an anonymous perspective
on um what happens if these deals don't
go the way you hope. And um I'd love to
hear you know just topline what happens
if you default on a 7A loan. Yeah. So
before I get into the meat of the
answer, I do want to share a disclaimer
which I hope you'd appreciate as an
attorney. So love every qualifier there
is. Yeah. Well, it's a very sensitive
topic, right? And so I want to make
clear that whatever views I express on
this episode, they're my own. I don't
necessarily reflect the views or the
opinions of or the policies of my
employer who's live oak bank or the
small business administration. The
conversation really is forformational
purposes only and should not be
considered legal or financial or tax
advice. So, I encourage everyone if this
is something you want to learn more
about or have an informed discussion for
your own circumstances, please talk with
a professional or talk to your own
lender if you need to. Again, we'll talk
more about this in terms of, you know,
what does this look like? What should I
do or what the options might be? But the
last thing I'll say is every loan and
business set of business circumstances
is unique. And so what I'm going to talk
about today, it's really more broad
brush strokes. It's not necessarily
going to be very prescriptive. Uh but
but with that being said, to answer your
question, it it really depends on a lot
of different things. So, and it might be
worth splitting this up into two
different perspectives. One is what can
you do before the deal closes to avoid
being this in situation in in the
situation in the first place. But then I
think what you're asking is it let's
fast forward if you've already closed
the deal. What does it look like? What
happens if if I've already taken that
plunge, the loan's closed and you know
whatever the circumstances are, things
are not going well. So the good news is
there is a process in place. And so even
if if something goes bump in the night,
the way this all works is it's not like
you're immediately put into liquidation.
Liquidation is generally when a lender
has determined that there's a low
likelihood of success for the business
and so they need to start recovery
basically the efforts to recover as much
of their uh their risk their exposure as
possible. Now I think most people
understand the SBA program the 7A
program it's a loan guarantee program.
So what that means is as a lender, most
of the time they have a guarantee for
75% of the loan. So if the bank makes a
loan for a million dollars, $250,000
would be their exposure. $750,000 would
be what the SBA guarantees to the to the
bank uh if if the loan does go into
liquidation. And there's a whole set of
procedures and and steps that happen
once a loan starts to quote unquote go
bad because going bad can mean different
things. Going bad doesn't mean
necessarily you've missed a payment, but
usually it starts with missing a
payment. So perhaps we can start there.
So So generally what happens is if if
you've missed a payment after 30 days
and again I want to stress this isn't
necessarily what even Live Oak does or
every any other SBA lender. They have
their own policies. Just as an aside,
one thing I do want to make sure
everyone's aware of, a document out
there called the uh
I have the link here and and maybe you
can post it in the show notes. Yeah.
Yeah. So, so it's publicly available.
This is not, you know, proprietary, but
the SBA has available. There's really
two documents I recommend everyone read
before they consider getting an SBA
loan. as it relates to this conversation
and this topic. There's a servicing and
liquidation manual. It's about 200 pages
long. Oh boy, that does sound like
everyone should read it. It's great
reading material. Keep it by the bedside
yet. It'll put you to sleep quickly, but
but it's actually the playbook that the
that the SBA puts out for all of the
lenders in the program to abide by. And
it doesn't get into explicit detail per
se in terms of you know if so and so
misses a payment you know this is the
exact thing that's going to happen but
it gives you the framework that lenders
have to follow in these situations and
it goes through orders of operations and
while I don't necessarily think someone
should go and read all 200 pages when
you have tools like chat GPT and Gemini
and all the others today you can really
use this to your advantage and inform
yourself and prepare yourself and
educate yourself in a way that doesn't
raise red flags in the same way going to
your lender and saying, "Hey, what
happens if I stop paying my loan?"
Right? That's right. You can ask them
that, but yeah, you you can ask them
that, but I just maybe don't don't maybe
don't ask them that until you know a
little bit more that's going on. Um, we
skated past so much value and it took me
a long time as somebody who was, you
know, ancillary to the lender. you know,
I'm just there helping. It took me a
long time to really uh understand the
background of the SBA and the way it
interplays with banks. Um, what I have
seen is if you're not a preferred
lender, it's really hard to get a deal
closed with a 7A loan because they have
to send it out to the government to
process and underwrite. But if you're a
preferred SBA lender, then you can
underwrite inhouse. So that was, you
know, from my perspective, one of the
big things like aha moments. And now
when a deal comes to to my desk and it's
you know it it happens a lot. Somebody
says I have a great relationship with my
local bank or whatever and they have an
SBA wing and you go are they a preferred
lender. This is so hard. Yeah. Um so I
really I always like that but but
another thing that you know it took a
little cognitive understanding and
correct me if my understanding is wrong
right because I'm kind of learning as I
go along. um is that uh you know the se
the SBA 78 loan program is kind of like
the FDIC, right? It's like they went to
banks and the government says, "Hey, you
know, like lending to small businesses
might be a little bit riskier, but we
want to encourage it because it's good
for the economy. So, we're going to
ensure these loans for up to 75%. And
because of that, you have this
additional assurance. you get this kind
of promise and it enables banks to go
out and make the loans that maybe some
of the banks wouldn't have felt
comfortable um championing. They would
have, you know, consolidated to the
biggest companies because they're the
most likely to. So it's a economic
measure and is that pretty accurate?
Yeah. Yeah, that's exactly right. So I I
think the idea was and they're always
updating the program. There's a new set
of rules. So, so the servicing manual
that I mentioned, that's kind of on the
back side after a loan has closed. On
the front side, there's the SOP, right?
And and that kind of lays out what the
criteria are for for eligibility, who
can get a loan, and then for lenders
participating in the program, what do
they have to do to to vet a borrower uh
before they close a loan? So, frankly, I
think both of those documents are are
really valuable and not a lot of people
are either aware are aware that they
exist or know how to access them. It's
it's all publicly available information.
We're all US taxpayers here. So, you
know, make these resources, you know,
avail yourself to them and read them and
educate yourself because it can make it
it can make a huge difference, you know,
as you prepare. It's not a I don't take
lightly and I I think most people
applying for a loan don't take lightly.
You know, you're putting a lot on the
line here. So, you want to know what's
at stake and you want to know how am I
going to get measured? How am I going to
get underwritten? And then when the loan
closes, how is it going to get serviced?
What does that look like? So, that is
true. I will say um and this is no knock
on any bank but um having read the SOPs,
one mantra that I center myself with is
it doesn't matter what I think the SOP
says. It matters what the bank thinks
it's because I have interpreted them
regularly very differently than the
bank. Um but it doesn't matter. My my
view is not important the banks as
important. So there is um they're not
always the most obvious interpretations
and there's a big team I assume that of
like lawyers and people and I've been in
those groups you know you can all come
out you can read the same thing and come
out with very different takes. So it
gets you part of the way there but it's
still a little bit nebulous how it's
going to be applied. So you have SOPs on
the front 100%. And then you have this
operating procedure on the back end for
you know if there's a liquidation. Um so
uh continue on. I'm glad I understand
where this fits in the world. Yeah. So,
so going back to kind of the the the key
question you asked, what happens? So, so
typically if someone misses a payment
after 30 days, the bank will likely send
a cure notice. So, it's more of a
courtesy, but it's it's essentially
telling the borrower, look, here's a
right for you to cure the problem. the
problem is you haven't paid us your most
recent monthly payment that's due and
here's a courtesy uh notice to give you
an opportunity to fix the issue. Maybe
you turned AC autoac off and didn't
manually schedule the payment. Uh maybe
it's a little bit more or uh
problematic. Maybe there's a cash flow
problem. usually around the the 45 to 60
day mark. Uh if there's not a response
or any kind of resolution, the loan and
it's typically at the 60-day mark, the
loan can get flagged and transferred to
special assets. So that sounds so scary.
I know. I know. and and mo mo most banks
have a special assets team. But
essentially what happens is for loans
that are on the fritz where you know
payments have been missed or borrowers
are not communicating uh our team the
servicesers the relationship manager if
we can't get a hold of someone generally
speaking once special assets gets
involved it it's the indication that
something has gone wrong and we're not
really getting or or don't feel like
we're getting close to a resolution. Um,
so, uh, I guess you could think of it as
a way for of the bank kind of rolling
their sleeves up and and getting ready
to to to try to work out a solution
here, whatever that might be. Sometimes
it could be, oh, I was out of the
country and you know, maybe it's a
soloreneur. They don't have a team in
place and um you know, something more uh
just a little bit more innocuous like
that or it could be more problematic and
and there's going to kind of be an
escalation uh which we can walk through
high level what what that typically
looks like. So, do you recommend the
missing a payment? Do I I do not
recommend it. No. No. I not, but you
know, does it does it make sense if
you're if you're in a cash crunch and
you're thinking, I think I might not be
able to make this payment, does it make
sense to do something like call somebody
first before you? Yes. So, so one one of
the biggest points I wanted to stress on
on today's discussion is communication
is the most important thing at the end
of the day because if you do not
communicate with the lender or you stop
communicating with the lender, you have
to understand is that the bank isn't
doing this to punish anyone or or doing
it for personal reasons. This is all
essentially a reflection of the legal
documents and the legal contractual
agreement. I know there's a lot of
paperwork that people sign when they
close a loan, but a lot of that stuff
they're signing, it's not just
prefuncter. There's stuff in there and
words have meaning and a lot of those
things you're agreeing to, you know,
there there's in these situations there
there's consequences for for actions.
Um, right. So if you miss a payment and
there's really no recourse, there's no
like communication, there's no
explanation for what's happening,
there's no context provided, what that
does is it deprivives the bank of any
ability or opportunity to understand
what's happening. And really what
happens in that scenario where there's
no communication is it drastically and
very quickly limits what the options are
for the bank. And and that's a huge deal
because if there's very proactive
communication and the borrower gets in
front of issues or sees something hap,
you know, coming from from a good ways
away time-wise and can tell the bank,
hey, look, what whatever the case might
be, I mean, I don't want to generalize,
but if it's going to likely or or
possibly result in a missed payment,
getting in front of that and having that
conversation with the bank, whether it's
Live Oak or whoever else, it can be the
difference between getting in into to
these later stages of of uh you know
exactly and avoiding that in the first
place. Right. You can it is possible and
if you go through that liquidation and
servicing manual that I mentioned a lot
of this is laid out there. Banks have
some tools available at their disposal
in terms of working with the customer to
to help address these situations when
the the going gets tough. we can make
and I'm not saying we will or you know
every case is unique and and so this is
not some kind of you know guaranteed
thing that's going to happen but banks
have the ability to modify terms we can
extend maturity dates we can uh grant
some degree of forbearance where where
there's a halt you know you can hold off
on a couple of payments if if it allows
someone to get back on their feet
whatever the case might be there can be
flexibility and those are options that
very quickly will often just get taken
off the table if no one's talking if no
one's you coming to the bank and being
open. So, a lack of communication is the
quickest way to to take something that's
maybe problematic but manageable and
turn it into a point, you know, get past
a point of no return, which obviously
nobody wants. Interesting. So, there is
kind of this balance. Um for me a lot of
my uh this question has come up a lot
before folks have gotten a loan but on
the rarer occasion that I get a call uh
after there's a loan it's been like
within the first year um with I think
usually you know you've normalized
things the transition is really hard
it's a cash flow crunch of a time
there's a lot of anxiety about just not
being able to like potentially not being
able to so the conversation I've had
sometimes is it seems like you're
nervous, not you're going to miss a
payment. So, and that is not a time
necessarily to talk to your bank. Like,
if you're not actually going to miss a
payment and you're just anxious about
the fact that you're having to get used
to this debt being on your shoulders,
that's different than, you know, okay,
well, I don't know that I'm going to be
able to make the ne next payment. Um,
I'm probably not going to and I need to
figure out something. though figuring
out that gray space, but it seems like
before that missed payment is missed,
definitely call the bank and see what
they can do. But I was curious um
because some of the stuff that I
researched in those cases was like maybe
the bank's position is different in the
first year versus subsequent years. Like
they particularly don't want you to
default in the first year. Yeah. So, so,
so what you're getting at is probably
the early loan default threshold. So to
what what happens is in in the first 18
months after a loan closes if it if
there is a default then the SBA
essentially conducts an audit like
automatically. So like the government
comes to the bank and they're like yeah
they're going to Exactly. Yeah. They're
going to they're going to audit the file
and and they're going to ask a lot of
questions. They're going to look at how
the bank underwrote the loan. they're
going. So, one of the things I should
mention is what's interesting with the
structure of the program with it being a
loan guarantee program and particularly
in cases where the bank is a preferred
lender you if if to remind folks if
you're a preferred lender like Live Oak
is and and most of the top lenders in
the country, they can essentially
underwrite, approve, and fund these
loans without the government looking
really at anything other than some
backend more preuncter checks where, you
we're running people through ELPS or
basically making sure no one's, you
know, on on naughty lists that would
preclude them from getting a loan.
Outside of that, most of all all of the
the process of approving someone, it
happens inhouse at the bank. And and the
reason that's a big deal in the context
of what you're talking about is the
government is still providing that
guarantee, right? to the bank and
therefore the customer, the borrower is
getting a a tremendous benefit by
getting access to this capital. So when
a loan goes bad, if it's in that first
18 months, the that guarantee is very
much in in question. It could be in
jeopardy. And that's a huge deal for the
bank because what went from a $250,000
exposure could potentially go to a a
million dollar exposure in that
million-doll example. if the SBA
concludes that the bank didn't follow
SOP, right? So that's that's why I mean
I would say a default and you know going
through liquidation at any point in the
process is is going to be a problem but
an early default in particular if it
happens in that first 18 months it just
raises more flags and there's more
scrutiny by SBA. Um and and that's why a
lot of banks are particularly sensitive
to that. Okay. So that's that's great
information. It's new to me. So ex
essentially if it happens in that first
18 months, it triggers this audit and if
the bank or if the government finds that
the bank didn't meet every single SOP or
you know they could pull their
guarantee. So um especially if you're in
the first 18 months, you're like work
with your bank. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. And
that's the that's the shaky time too
where you know you're you're more likely
like you some of these tools that you
mentioned that might be available but
certainly are not promised like
forbearance or extending maturity dates
and stuff that could have the effect
especially those first 18 months of
getting you over the hump. So that seems
that's super interesting. That's good
information to have. So, what happens if
you go along and um you know, you're
just like in a normal period of time,
you miss a payment um or you know, you
your banker works with you and you still
can't make it work. Um and you go to
special assets, which I'm imagining they
all have shaved heads and they're very
intimidating. Maybe like one guy has a
like a scar all the way.
We recruit uh from from uh recently
released inmates exclusively. Yeah.
Well, I worked at a war crimes tribunal
in the HEG and there was a division that
was like it was like I'm describing. So
that's what a victim is like financial
diligence and they were all super
intimidating but their job was like to
go to the region and find all of the
assets of these people being accused of
war crimes and make sure that they you
know repo them basically. So similar
maybe you could recruit from there just
like if you
they're what I mean I I know they get a
bad rep. It's almost like, you know,
auditors, right? No one wants to hear
from the auditor, but it's an important
job and someone has to do it. And um,
you know, I I feel for them because
they're I know most people don't
probably think about, you know, the bank
and the people coming after that. It's
an adver they view it as an adversarial
relationship, but, you know, they're
dealing with people who are often going
through, you know, the the worst moment
in their lives or whether it's
personally or professionally, often
times both.
And it's uh it's it's challenging work,
but it's it's really important. Uh but
you know, you you I can't stress enough
how important it is to have the right
people doing that type of work because
you you do have to work with people who
are going through often what are extreme
hardships. And I mean, think about being
in that situation where you know, you
bought a business and whatever the case
might be, it's not working out. and you
have either hundreds of thousands or
millions of dollars in debt that you're
not able to pay back. It's incredibly
stressful and have for us, you know,
having a team and and people in place
who can be patient and who can be
understanding and sympathetic but also
honest and and you know clear about
what's happening and I mean it's not
easy. It's not an easy job. Uh so I feel
for I would want it although that
division at the war crimes tribunal was
very fun. they were very nice people.
Um, so, uh, but yeah, I I hear what
you're saying there. One thing that I
constantly am curious about is, you
know, you have the collateral and what I
do primarily with accounting practices,
it's a cash flow lending thing as
professional services firm. So, it's not
like you have a warehouse of accounting
inventory. You know, you've got like
usually five grand of old office
furniture and a copy or scanner that's
probably leased anyways. And um and then
there's just the client list. So um that
I've been interested like to what degree
does the bank try to make something out
of the business itself versus do they
just skip straight to like hard assets
like okay well their house is on the
line. We know we can take you know the
house. Let's get that before anything
anybody else any other lenders try to
scoop things up. Yeah. Well, it it's a
challenge reflective of the industry and
as you allude to by and large, you know,
these are professional services ind uh
businesses. So, there's not a ton of
hard assets, at least on the business
side, right? There's not going to be
much in the way of recovery when we're
talking about if there's a physical
office space, you know, cubicles, some
office furniture, laptops,
and and that's just an inherent risk of
the industry in in generally working
with professional services firms. Um,
now that often what that results in is
is we're looking on the personal side,
right? So, whether that's equity in
somebody's home, if they have other
assets, right, if they have, you know,
vehicles, boats, um, there's Yeah. But
it it's it's kind of just a known risk
that if you're making a loan to a
professional services firm, you know,
it's it's an elevated there's an
elevated risk that if things go bump in
the night, the recovery value on the
business side of things is is likely
going to be very limited, which is why,
frankly, the SBA program is so valuable,
right? I think in a conventional lending
setting, that would likely be a very
difficult uh it would be a difficult
loan to get approved for. uh with the
SBA program being primarily cash flow
based, right? It opens up a lot of doors
in cases where I think from a
conventional lending standpoint, it
would be really hard to get a yes. I see
what you mean there. That does make
sense. Do you do I mean does special
assets do anything with the company? I
mean, do they try to call the seller and
say, "Hey, can you take this back over
or like let's another bank?" I haven't
seen that. Um, I mean, the the thing is
if whatever the issues are that are
leading to special assets to get
involved in the first place, it's
probably going to make that business
pretty low value in the in, you know, at
the end of the day. And so, even if you
like got a broker involved and tried to
have a fire sale or or or sell, you
know, some of the the client list, I I
think the recovery value there is
probably going to be pretty limited. I I
don't want to say it's it's not
possible. Um, you know, I've I've heard
of cases, not necessarily for accounting
firms. Okay. I I've certainly seen cases
for other businesses that where where
there's like a kind of a forced sale or
or, you know, encouragement of of a
sale. Um, I personally had been involved
in a situation where uh when I first
started at the bank almost a decade ago,
uh, I mentioned I'm based in DC. I have
a government contracting background, but
there was a case where an individual had
purchased a a government contractor and
it wasn't working out. They weren't
winning as much work. I think they just
underestimated the uh the the difficulty
of running a business. And then in that
industry in particular, uh and
interestingly enough, we uh we we
brokered like a loan assumption. So, one
of the things you can do with an SBA
loan is someone else can assume an SBA
7A loan. Okay. And uh I haven't seen
that yet for a CPA firm. Doesn't mean it
can't happen. Yeah. But what's unique
about the industry is, you know,
customers can come and go very quickly.
And it's a little bit different with
like a government contracting firm. like
you you win a contract with the
government that's pretty much staying in
place and it's you can transfer it,
right? You can buy that firm anyway. So,
it it it is possible. I don't I don't
think it happens very often and and so
you know, it's all goodwill, you know,
it is all goodwill. I um that's
interesting uh because you know that
means hey
you definitely want to pay attention to
the personal assets that are in play
here because that's going to be the the
pretty much the straight step that the
bank's going to take is to get to those
assets. They're not going to really like
waste wait around trying to make
something of the business itself
necessarily.
Yeah. But but to the earlier point, the
sooner that we're told that there's
issues, depending on what those issues
are,
remember what I said, the sooner we're
pulled in, the more opportunity and the
more time that that gives us to get
creative and to work with the customer
to try to troubleshoot here. I mean,
there's been cases where we've assisted
with bringing consultants in and and
helping with marketing, helping them
spruce up their website, helping them. I
mean, there's again, these are all case
dependent. And yeah, and and so it I
don't want to say because I've seen it,
it's going to happen in someone's unique
circumstances, but
the earlier you notify the bank that
there's a challenge and we get pulled
in, the more of an opportunity that
gives us to help rectify the situation.
The later we're told about something or
if we're just not told at all, Yeah.
that really ties our hands and therefore
limits the options for the customer as
well. I think the natural
instinct for a lot of people when this
happens is is to kind of retract and get
into a defensive posture. And there's
all types of other dynamics at play
here. I mean, there's there's emotions,
there's people, you know, feeling
ashamed, feeling embarrassed
and whatever whatever it is, you know,
if it if it results in them going silent
that Yeah. that that makes it really
hard to to troubleshoot at all, right?
You can't fix what you don't know. Yeah.
What you're not aware of. So I think
once special assets gets involved you
know we typically will there's a I think
it's in the servicing manual uh that I
mentioned uh we'll have to do a site
visit right so to your question like we
will in those cases we'll we'll visit
the customer and look at what's
happening on on the ground right we'll
we'll see um if if there are any assets
in the office space talk as much as we
can with the customer face to face try
to understand what's happening
Um, this doesn't really pertain or or
probably isn't particularly relevant to
the customer directly, but in the back
on the back end, and this is pretty
uniform, I think across most banks,
they're all going to have their own like
riskra
pro uh system in place. All it is is uh
it's the way that the bank measures the
the risk of all their different loans in
their portfolio, right? and and some
every day, every week, every month, you
know, loans are getting upgraded,
downgraded, right? But yeah, it's it's a
way to kind of measure the the uh
strength uh of of that lending portfolio
and and then also to help allocate
resources and attention in terms of
where do we need to direct
resources and marshall resources uh to
to help folks where where they might
need help or or for the bank ultimately
to try to increase the likelihood of
recovery. Right. Yeah.
So, if you're um that's interesting. It
makes sense that you would because
obviously the bank isn't going to want
to make a dis disproportionate number of
risky loans. So, you're going to have
certain number of ones of each um
rating. um if so the personal assets
that are guar you're guaranteeing like
the home which is you know the the
difference um of your primary residence
uh you know and how much of that can be
seized is a little bit state specific.
There's some states that have like a
homestead exemption of 100% and then
there's like hilarious ones like
California's homestead exemption is is
like for $70,000 if your home which like
in California is a riot like that's not
helpful to anyone. Um don't quote me on
that. I don't think that's exactly
accurate, but you get the context. No,
but you're you're spot on. I think some
states have like a $10,000 exception,
which is how nice of them. This um but
if you know, if you're looking, you're
running your business, you have these
loans um already, um you're living your
life. I mean, they're 10-year terms, so
you've got a lot of life to live in 10
years um as a professional. So, you're
going along, you're acquiring more
assets. Let's say you're buying a second
home or a rental property. Are all of
those additional assets going to be
seizable by your prior prior
pre-existing SBA 7A loan? Does it like
get updated or is it kind of fixed based
on what you have at the time you take it
out? So, and I wish it was a clear black
and white answer. Um, but I think it it
will depend. So, so what you're bringing
up and it's an important distinction to
make
when you're applying for a loan. There's
a couple of things I think most people
are aware of if if they're thinking
about getting an SBA loan. One is the
personal guarantee, right? So that
personal guarantee is unconditional and
it's it's not limited. It's it's
obviously it's going to generally be
limited by whatever the exposure is, but
the actual guarantee is is is unlimited
and unconditional. But that's different
than an asset specific lean that is
placed on a particular asset. So, one of
the other requirements that I think most
people are aware of, at least in the
conversations I have with prospects, is
uh SBA requires if you have 25% equity
or more in a residence uh if there's a
collateral shortfall, you have to pledge
and and again, it's an SBA rule, not a
live oak specific rule, but if you have
25% equity or more and there's a
collateral shortfall, which there almost
always is within with a professional
services uh business, they have to put a
lean on that property. Now, most of the
time there's a mortgage in place, right?
Most people uh have a mortgage, so the
bank is subordinate or in a second
position to whoever that lender is. And
that's that's pretty much, you know,
that's the rule. So there is a
distinction between having that personal
guarantee out there which theoretically
puts in into play all of the assets that
that guarantor has on their personal
balance sheet and the actual specific
lean for for an asset. So the guarantee
is less it because it's not tied to a
specific asset. Yeah. It there's there's
a little bit more
Well, you would have to I imagine it's
less direct, right? So, exactly. So,
there's more that can change, right? The
borrower could dispose of it, could
transfer ownership to somebody else. Um,
the bank, I'm going to go after the
properties that there's a lean on first,
you know, and just to use my own like
situation, I've had my house for a long
time, so I have a lot of equity. So, I
have like $700,000 of equity or
something in my house, but my mortgage
is, you know, 400,000. So, yeah, like
they would get the the mortgager would
get 400,000. you guys could take 300,000
and you know but and then the shortfall
there's that personal guarantee but I I
think like mechanically you might have
to go and get a judgment for phys like
you'd have to sue me and get a judgment
against me and then have you know the
whole legal process of collecting on
collateral that I own um which is
additional kind of headache beyond so
you know there's I see what you mean
there's a group of things that are, you
know, there's a lean on that are going
to come first and then there's like the
general personal guarantee that goes to
anything that I have kind of less
directly. Exactly. And and with that
personal guarantee, you know, there's
less uh certainty I suppose the the bank
has compared to that that specific
asset. Um in any case, what we're
talking about here is typically, you
know, pretty far down the road. I don't
want to generalize again too much, but a
lot of times when we're getting to this
point about, you know, assets being
liquidated,
most of the time I think folks head have
already are in the process of filing for
bankruptcy, mostly chapter 7, but not
necessarily just chapter 7. So, um, you
know, if you're getting to this point or
thinking you might be on track to get to
that point, I mean, I would hope at this
point you've already spoken with an
attorney and bankruptcy attorney and you
Exactly. Yeah. And there there's even
attorneys out there with specialization
in working with like offers and
compromise with SBA lenders. So there's
a whole process uh that you know you you
can learn more about in in in those
cases, but it's going to be so
individual in in the state you're in is
is also a huge factor. So um it's true.
And the bankruptcy attorneys are, you
know, this is all they do. So, I
certainly don't dabble and and they're
they're also uh sweet angels for
participating in such a challenging
experience people have. Well, this has
been really helpful and I I don't want
to I know it might feel like a downer to
talk about it, but so I wanted to end by
being like descriptive about how rare
this is. you know, the 70 low program
does there's very few defaults it
because you do underwrite um pretty
conservatively, you know, it's not like
it's intended to make banks a little bit
more comfortable with things like
professional services firms and
underwriting them, but it's not like
you're just throwing money at people.
So, of course. Yeah. I mean, when I have
tried calling around and ask like, "Have
you seen somebody default? Have you seen
I have to talk to a lot of people and
there's just a couple of occasions that
people are all kind of referencing um
anecdotally. So I mean do you want to
say anything about how uncommon it is?
Well yeah I mean you can look up the
default rates by industry but I think
for accounting professionals
industrywide and I say industrywide like
in the SBA lending world for there's
about four NYX codes we can limit this
to. Um, these are the sixdigit like
industry codes that the I think it's
NICS. Yeah. N AICS stands for North
American Industrial Classification
System if if I have that right. And know
it stood for anything. I mean, so good.
Yeah. But but but there's about four
that that I'm referring to in terms of
the industries that I work on. And if
you just narrow narrow the lens to those
four, I think the default rate over the
last 10 years is in the low single
digits. Maybe five five to 6% 4%
something like that. And keep in mind
default is not the same thing as charged
off. Those are not the same thing. So
the actual so what that means is a lot
of loans that default they they stay in
a defaulted status but then they get
back on track and and and so there's you
know recoveries made and uh and folks
you know generally get back into acrual
status. There's charge offs which are
kind of the end result of a loan truly
going bad where there's a certain
exposure. Maybe there's some recovery uh
of of that whatever that amount is but
there's some loss and then the bank will
will will charge that off. The charge
off rate is I think sub 1% something may
maybe. Yeah. So to your point it's it's
so rare exceedingly low but it does
happen. And so to my earlier point when
we started because we've done like in if
you look at the last decade I think Live
Oak has done almost double the amount of
loans in this industry uh to the next
number to I think it's Wells Fargo. Um
and I'm not saying that to to brag. I'm
I'm really it's more of a point of of
statistical probability because we've
done the most amount of lending. We've
by extension seen the most amount of
deals probably that have gone bad and
we've seen the the range of reasons that
happen. So, it's really important when
folks are picking a lender or talking to
different lenders. You know, we're going
to help customers be put in the best
position to succeed and to avoid some of
these uh you know, these mistakes or or
lapses of judgment. You know, every new
deal that goes bad, you learn something
from it. And as a result, and this is
true for every bank, they're probably
going to tweak their credit policy
slightly to account for that in the
future, right? So that's really
important, right? We we I think a lot of
people approach getting a loan as like
it's a commodity and frankly like
whoever says yes to me, that's who I'm
going to work with. And I really
encourage folks if they're getting told
like from a particular lender like
here's why we're not comfortable with
this deal. even if they can get a yes
from someone else. I think I really it's
worth pausing and and wondering and and
exploring like why is the bank saying
this? It's not we're not doing it to be
a a thorn in your side. We're doing it
because there's a there's you know scars
that we have we can point to in the past
that that you know inform our approach
there. So that's really critical and
that helps kind of add color to what
I've experienced where I said earlier
the SOPs it doesn't matter what I think
they say but you know the credit
policies are playing in there and the
experiences of the bank are playing in
there so I might say yeah it says you
can you know do X but you guys are
coming at it with a lot more experience
and um also before we uh close up I
wanted to make sure you got a chance to
talk about the express product that you
guys do super cool I do a ton of um you
know deals below $5 million, but a lot
of those deals are also you know
sometimes tuckins or add-ons or whatever
you want to call them or they're just
smaller. They're below $500,000 and um
you guys have a great product for that.
We do. Yes. Thank you. Appreciate you
bringing that up. So we launched last
year at the beginning of 24 our live oak
express product. It actually includes an
SBA option and a conventional option.
Most of it is is SBA, but to your point,
the the biggest takeaway, it's for loans
up to 500,000. And we can actually
underwrite and close and fund in as
little as a few days. Usually, it's one
to two weeks on average, but I've seen
some close in in less than a week, which
is remarkable if you know how long it
takes to underwrite and Yeah. and get
closed.
Yeah. So, it it's it's an awesome option
if if it applies to you, right? If
you're looking at a smaller deal, we
have a streamlined application process.
There's a digital application. It it
really removes a lot of the friction
that's there in your kind of more
standard uh typical underwriting
timeline. So, I think we ended up doing
over 100 million worth of express loans
last year and we expect that probably go
up by almost a factor of 10 this year.
So, it's a really awesome product. um
obviously not the not the right fit if
you're looking for a much larger deal.
Um but but it is u it's a wonderful
tool. So yeah, we'd love to to talk with
anyone who might want to learn more.
Well um so if anybody wants to learn
more, we'll Eric Rabinovich Live Oak
reach out and um if you found this
content helpful, please like and
subscribe and engage with it. And thanks
for coming on, Eric. It was wonderful.
Thank Thank you, sir. Appreciate it.
Take care. I'll talk to you soon. You
too. Take care.